Guide to the Charles Andrews Fenton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Andrews Fenton papers
1954-1960
MS 206
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
(17 boxes)
The papers consist almost entirely of bibliographical material, newspaper magazine articles, excerpts from books and news dispatches collected for his proposed work on American literary approaches to the Spanish Civil War. There is also a small amount of correspondence (1954-1960). Important correspondents are Daniel Aaron, Claude G. Bowers, Granville Hicks, Rolfe Humphries, Mark Schorer and F. Jay Taylor.
Fenton, Charles A., 1919-1960
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Andrews Fenton, Jr., in 1961.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Andrews Fenton was born in Springfield, Massachusetts, in 1919. As an author and educator, Fenton wrote such volumes as: The Apprenticeship of Ernest Hemmingway: The Early Years (1954); and Stephen Vincent Benet: The Life and Times of an American Man of Letters (1958). He also edited Best Short Stories of World War II (1957); and Stephen Vincent Benet's Selected Letters (1960). He taught English Literature at Yale from 1948-1958. Fenton died on July 21, 1960.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Andrews Fenton Papers consist of bibliographical and research notes collected by Fenton in preparation for a proposed work on the American literary approaches to the Spanish Civil War. The notes include excerpts from and references to newspaper and magazine articles, books, and news dispatches. The papers, which were donated to Yale University by Charles Andrews Fenton, Jr., in 1961, are arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
A single folder of correspondence (box 5, folder 115) contains letters to individuals listed in "List of Correspondents."
See: List of Correspondents.
American literature; Literature -- History and criticism; Radicalism; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939; Authors; Educators; Aaron, Daniel, 1912-2016; Bowers, Claude G. (Claude Gernade), 1879-1958; Fenton, Charles A., 1919-1960; Hicks, Granville, 1901-1982; Humphries, Rolfe; Schorer, Mark, 1908-1977; Taylor, F. Jay (Foster Jay), 1923-2011
- Inventory
  - Air war (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Albacete (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alcazar (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Allen, Jay (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Almeria (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alvah, Bessie, Men in Battle (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - America (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Artists and Writers Committee (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Board of Guardians For Basque Refugee Children (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Friends of Spanish Democracy (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American League Against War and Fascism (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - American Mercury (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Relief Ships for Spain (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Spanish Relief Fund (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - American Union For Nationalist Spain (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Anarchism (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Anderson, Sherwood (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Anti-Crusade (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Anti-Communist (Box 1, Folder 21)
    General note
    See also: box 5, folders 105-109
  - Arrival in Spain (Box 1, Folder 22)
    See also: box 1, folder 3
  - Art (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Artists (Box 1, Folder 24)
    See also: box 11, folder 245
  - Associated Press (AP) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Atmosphere (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
  - Auden, W.H. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Authors (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Author's League (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Azana (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Background--Anti-1920's (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Background--World War I (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Background--Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Ballov, Jenny, Spanish Prelude (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Barcelona (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Barsky, Dr. Edward (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Basque Refugee Children (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Bates, Ralph (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Battalion (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Belchite (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Belloc, HiLaire (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Benet, James (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Benet, S.V. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Bernanos (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Bethune, Dr. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Bibliography--Spanish Civil War (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Bilbao (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Blockade (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Blum, Leon (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Borrow, George (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Bowers, Claude My Mission in Spain, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 54-55)
  - Brazil (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Brenan, The Face of Spain (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Brigade (Box 2, Folder 58-61)
  - Brigade, André Battalion (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Brigade, Dimitrov Battalion (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Brigade, Lincoln Battalion (Box 2, Folder 64-66)
  - Brihuega (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Brown, Heywood (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Browder (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Brutality (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Bullfights (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Canada (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Canby, Henry (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Cardozo, Harold, The March of a Nation (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Carney, William P. (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Casualties (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Caudwell, Christopher (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Censorship (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Chamberlain (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Chapter Headings (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Chaves Nogales, Manuel, Heroes and Beasts of Spain (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Check and Check and Transfer (Box 3, Folder 82-87)
  - Chicago Tribune (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Christian Science Monitor (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Chronology (Box 4, Folder 90-95)
  - Church (Box 4, Folder 96-98)
  - Churchill, Winston (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Civil Guards (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Colum, Mary (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Combat (Box 4, Folder 102)
    See also: box 16, folder 406
  - Commissars (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Commonweal (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Communist Influence (Box 5, Folder 105-109)
  - Concentration Camps (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Congress of Writers (Box 5, Folder 111-112)
  - Copa, Robert (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Correspondence--Spanish War, 1954-1960 (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Cowley, Malcolm (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Crusade (Box 6, Box 5, Folder 116-129)
  - Crusade Pro Franco (Box 6, Folder 130-131)
  - Cuba (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Culture (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - Daily Worker (Box 6, Folder 134)
    See also: box 13, folder 323
  - Davies, John Langdon, Behind the Spanish Barricades (Box 6, Folder 135)
  - del Vayo, Freedom's Battle (Box 6, Folder 136-137)
  - de Madariaga (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - de Rivera, Jose Primo (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - Deserters (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - Discipline (Box 6, Folder 141)
  - Dos Passos, John (Box 6, Folder 142-143)
  - Dreiser, Theodore (Box 6, Folder 144-145)
  - Dunn, James (Box 6, Folder 146)
    See also: box 15, folders 394-395
  - Ebro (Box 6, Folder 147)
  - Eden, Anthony (Box 6, Folder 148)
  - Elliot, Paul Life and Death of a Spanish Town, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 149)
  - The End, 1938 (Box 7, Box 6, Folder 150-152)
  - England (Box 7, Folder 153-155)
  - English (Box 7, Folder 156)
  - Enlistments (Box 7, Folder 157-159)
  - Epilogue (Box 8, Box 7, Folder 160-168)
  - Equipment (Box 8, Folder 169)
  - Excerpts
    - Handwritten copies of newspaper articles (Box 8, Folder 170-171)
    - Works of various writers (Box 8, Folder 172-180)
  - Exile (Box 9, Folder 181)
  - Expatriate (Box 9, Folder 182)
  - Fast, Howard (Box 9, Folder 183)
  - Federal Writers Project (Box 9, Folder 184)
  - Fiction (Box 9, Folder 185-186)
  - Fifth Column (Box 9, Folder 187)
  - Finances (Box 9, Folder 188)
  - Fischer, Louis (Box 9, Folder 189)
  - Foster Parent's Plan for Children in Spain (Box 9, Folder 190)
  - Fox, Ralph (Box 9, Folder 191)
  - France (Box 9, Folder 192)
  - Franco (Box 9, Folder 193)
  - Franco, Ramon (Box 9, Folder 194)
  - Frank, Waldo (Box 9, Folder 195)
  - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Battalion (Box 9, Folder 196)
  - Front Organizations (Box 9, Folder 197)
  - Germany (Box 9, Folder 198-199)
  - Gide, André (Box 9, Folder 200)
  - Goldman, Emma (Box 9, Folder 201)
  - Guadalajara (Box 9, Folder 202)
  - Guernica (Box 9, Folder 203)
  - Guerrilla (Box 9, Folder 204)
  - Hayes, Cardinal (Box 9, Folder 205)
  - Hearst, William Randolph (Box 9, Folder 206)
  - Heart of Spain (Box 9, Folder 207)
  - Hemingway, Ernest (Box 10, Folder 208-209)
  - History (Box 10, Folder 210)
  - Hollywood (Box 10, Folder 211)
  - Honighen, Frank C., ed. Nothing but Danger (Box 10, Folder 212)
  - Hospitals (Box 10, Folder 213)
    See also: box 12, folder 287
  - Hughes, Langston (Box 10, Folder 214)
  - Hull (Box 10, Folder 215)
  - Humphries, Rolfe, And Spain Sings (Box 10, Folder 216)
  - Ickes (Box 10, Folder 217)
  - Illustrations (Box 10, Folder 218)
  - Intellectuals (Box 10, Folder 219)
  - International Congress of Writers, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 220)
  - International Publishers Inc. (Box 10, Folder 221)
  - Irish (Box 10, Folder 222)
  - Irun (Box 10, Folder 223)
  - Italians (Box 10, Folder 224)
  - Italian Anti-Fascist Committee (Box 10, Folder 225)
  - Italy (Box 10, Folder 226)
  - Ivens, Joris (Box 10, Folder 227)
  - Japan (Box 10, Folder 228)
  - Jarama (Box 10, Folder 229)
  - Johnstone, Nancy, Hotel in Spain (Box 10, Folder 230)
  - Joint Committee to Lift the Embargo (Box 10, Folder 231)
  - Journalists (Box 11, Box 10, Folder 232-241)
    - Pro-Franco (Box 11, Folder 242-244)
  - Kent, Rockwell (Box 11, Folder 245)
  - Knoblaugh, Edward H., Correspondent in Spain (Box 11, Folder 246)
  - Koestler, Arthur, Spanish Testament (Box 11, Folder 247)
  - Krivitsky (Box 11, Folder 248)
  - La Pasionaria (Box 11, Folder 249)
  - Lardner, James (Box 11, Folder 250)
  - Latin America (Box 11, Folder 251)
  - Lead (Box 11, Folder 252)
  - League for Cultural Freedom and Socialism (Box 11, Folder 253)
  - League of American Writers (Box 11, Folder 254-255)
  - League of Nations (Box 11, Folder 256)
  - Leave (Box 12, Folder 257)
  - Left Book Club (Box 12, Folder 258)
  - Lerner, Max (Box 12, Folder 259)
  - Letters to the Editor (Box 12, Folder 260)
  - Literary Influences (Box 12, Folder 261)
  - London Daily Express (Box 12, Folder 262)
  - London Daily Herald (Box 12, Folder 263)
  - London Daily Mail (Box 12, Folder 264)
  - London Daily Telegram (Box 12, Folder 265)
  - London Times (Box 12, Folder 266)
  - Lorca (Box 12, Folder 267)
  - Lunn, Arnold, Spanish Rehearsal (Box 12, Folder 268)
  - Lyons, Eugene (Box 12, Folder 269)
  - Mackenzie-Papineau (Box 12, Folder 270)
  - MacLeish, Archibald (Box 12, Folder 271)
  - Madrid (Box 12, Folder 272-275)
  - Magazines (Box 12, Folder 276)
  - Malaga (Box 12, Folder 277)
  - Malraux, André, Man's Hope (Box 12, Folder 278)
  - Manchester Guardian (Box 12, Folder 279)
  - Marcel, Acier, ed. From Spanish Trenches (Box 12, Folder 280)
  - Marty, André (Box 12, Folder 281)
  - Marxism (Box 12, Folder 282-284)
  - Matthews, H.L. (Box 12, Folder 285)
  - Medical Bureau and North American Committee... (Box 12, Folder 286)
  - Medical Unit (Box 12, Folder 287)
    See also: box 10, folder 213
  - Merriman, Robert (Box 12, Folder 288)
  - Mexico (Box 12, Folder 289)
  - Mexico City (Box 12, Folder 290)
  - Military (Box 12, Folder 291-292)
  - Minorca (Box 13, Folder 293)
  - Modern Age Books (Box 13, Folder 294)
  - Mola (Box 13, Folder 295)
  - Mooney Machine Gun Company (Box 13, Folder 296)
  - Moore, Judge Robert (Box 13, Folder 297)
  - Moors (Box 13, Folder 298)
  - Morale (Box 13, Folder 299-300)
  - Moscow Trials (Box 13, Folder 301)
  - Motion Picture Artists Committee (Box 13, Folder 302)
  - Munich (Box 13, Folder 303)
  - Nation (Box 13, Folder 304)
  - Negrin (Box 13, Folder 305)
  - Nelson, Steve (Box 13, Folder 306)
  - New Republic, "They Still Draw Pictures" (Box 13, Folder 307-309)
  - New York Daily News (Box 13, Folder 310)
  - New Yorker (Box 13, Folder 311)
  - New York Fund Raising Organizations (Box 13, Folder 312-315)
  - New York Herald Tribune (Box 13, Folder 316)
  - New York Post (Box 13, Folder 317)
  - New York Sun (Box 13, Folder 318)
  - New York Times (Box 13, Folder 319)
    See also: box 3, folder 75
  - Non-Intervention (Box 13, Folder 320-321)
  - North American Committee For Spanish Democracy (Box 13, Folder 322)
  - North, Joe (Box 13, Folder 323)
  - Officers (Box 13, Folder 324)
    See also: box 2, folders 58-61
  - O'Neill, Eugene (Box 13, Folder 325)
  - Orwell, George (Box 13, Folder 326)
  - Paris Herald (Box 13, Folder 327)
  - Paul, Elliot (Box 13, Folder 328)
  - Pay (Box 13, Folder 329)
  - Pegler, Westbrook (Box 13, Folder 330)
  - People (Box 13, Folder 331)
  - Picasso, Pablo (Box 13, Folder 332)
  - Pilots (American) (Box 13, Folder 333)
  - Poetry (Box 13, Folder 334)
  - Politics (Box 13, Folder 335-337, Box 14)
  - Portugal (Box 14, Folder 338)
  - Posters (Box 14, Folder 339)
  - Prieto (Box 14, Folder 340)
  - Primitivism (Box 14, Folder 341)
  - Prisoners (Box 14, Folder 342)
  - Proletarian Background (Box 14, Folder 343)
  - Propaganda (Box 14, Folder 344-345)
  - Public Opinion (Box 14, Folder 346)
  - Quakers (Box 14, Folder 347)
  - Quiepo de Llano (Box 14, Folder 348)
  - Quintanilla (Box 14, Folder 349)
  - Rations (Box 14, Folder 350)
  - Reader's Digest (Box 14, Folder 351)
  - Red Cross, American (Box 14, Folder 352)
  - Refugees (Box 14, Folder 353)
  - Refugee Scholarship and Peace Campaign (Box 14, Folder 354)
  - Regler, Gustave, The Great Crusade (Box 14, Folder 355)
  - Relief Work (Box 14, Folder 356)
  - Religion (Box 14, Folder 357)
  - Repatriation (Box 14, Folder 358)
  - Research Council--Spanish War (Box 14, Folder 359)
  - Reviews (Box 14, Folder 360-363)
  - Rolfe, Edwin Lincoln Battalion, 1939 (Box 15, Folder 364-365)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano (Box 15, Folder 366-367)
  - Russia in Spain (Box 15, Folder 368)
  - Saturday Review of Literature (Box 15, Folder 369)
  - Scientists (Box 15, Folder 370)
  - Sedgewick, Ellery (Box 15, Folder 371)
  - Seldes (Box 15, Folder 372)
  - Sender, Counter-Attack in Spain (Box 15, Folder 373)
  - Sheean, Not Peace But a Sword (Box 15, Folder 374)
  - Society For Technical Aid to Spain (Box 15, Folder 375)
  - Sommerfield, John, Volunteer in Spain (Box 15, Folder 376)
  - Spain (Box 15, Folder 377-380)
  - Spain in Flames (Box 15, Folder 381)
  - Spain in Revolt (Box 15, Folder 382)
  - Spain--News dispatches (Box 15, Folder 383-384)
  - Spanish Child Welfare Associations of America (Box 15, Folder 385)
  - The Spanish Earth (Box 15, Folder 386)
  - Spanish Intellectual Aid (Box 15, Folder 387)
  - Spanish War (Box 15, Folder 388-392)
  - Spender, Stephen (Box 15, Folder 393)
  - State Department (Box 15, Folder 394-395)
  - Sumner Wells (Box 16, Folder 396)
  - Symbols (Box 16, Folder 397)
  - Tablet (Box 16, Folder 398)
  - Tervel (Box 16, Folder 399)
  - Themes (Box 16, Folder 400)
  - Thomas, Norman (Box 16, Folder 401)
  - Thompson, Dorothy (Box 16, Folder 402)
  - Time Inc. (Box 16, Folder 403)
  - Tinker, F.G., Some Still Live (Box 16, Folder 404)
  - Topography (Box 16, Folder 405)
  - Training (Box 16, Folder 406)
    See also: box 4, folder 102
  - Trotsky (Box 16, Folder 407)
  - Unamuno (Box 16, Folder 408)
  - Union Background (Box 16, Folder 409)
    See also: box 14, folder 343
  - United American Spanish Aid Committee (Box 16, Folder 410)
  - United Editorial Limited (Box 16, Folder 411)
  - United Spanish Committee (Box 16, Folder 412)
  - United Youth Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy (Box 16, Folder 413)
  - United States (Box 16, Folder 414)
  - United States: attitudes
    - General (Box 16, Folder 415-416)
    - American History (Box 16, Folder 417)
    - American Reading (Box 16, Folder 418)
    - Businessman (Box 16, Folder 419)
    - Capitalism (Box 16, Folder 420)
    - Civil Liberties (Box 16, Folder 421)
    - Colleges (Box 16, Folder 422)
    - Congress (Box 16, Folder 423)
    - Dies Committee (Box 16, Folder 424)
    - Doctors (Box 16, Folder 425)
    - Embargo (Box 16, Folder 426)
    - Lobbyists (Box 16, Folder 427)
    - Military (Box 16, Folder 428)
    - Neutrality (Box 16, Folder 429)
    - Pacifism (Box 17, Box 16, Folder 430-431)
  - United States: press (Box 17, Folder 433)
  - Valencia (Box 17, Folder 434)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Battalion (Box 17, Folder 435)
  - War, A Literary (Box 17, Folder 436-438)
  - Washington Committee To Lift The Spanish Embargo (Box 17, Folder 439)
  - Watson, Keith Scott, Single To Spain (Box 17, Folder 440)
  - White, David McK. (Box 17, Folder 441)
  - The Will Of The People (Box 17, Folder 442)
  - Wilson, Edmund (Box 17, Folder 443)
  - Withdrawal (Box 17, Folder 444)
  - Wolfe, Thomas (Box 17, Folder 445)
  - World Committee Against War and Fascism (Box 17, Folder 446)
  - World War II (Box 17, Folder 447-449)
  - Wright, Richard (Box 17, Folder 450)
  - Writers, 1950-1959 (Box 17, Folder 451)
- List of Correspondents
  - Aaron, Daniel: TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Stanford, California, 1959 January 5 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Bowers, Claude G. (b. 1879): 5 TL to F. Jay Taylor,; New York, 1954 January 25, February 15, July 16; 1955 June 6, September 2 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Brooks, Robin: 2 TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Rochester, N.Y., 1960 April 7, 25 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Clark, Alexander P.: TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Princeton, N.J., 1959 May 28 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Farrar, John (b. 1896): TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; New York, N.Y., 1958 October 14 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Fenton, Charles A. (1919-1960): TLS to the Librarian, St. Louis Post-Dispatch,; St. Louis, Mo., 1959 December 16 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Henle, James: TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; New York, N.Y., 1959 April 26 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Hicks, Granville (b. 1901): TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Grafton, N.Y., 1959 May 28 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Humphries, Rolfe: 2 TLS to Charles A. Fenton; also 1 ALS,; Amherst, Mass., 1959 April 14, May 6, 14 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Kahn, Herman (b. 1922): TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Hyde Park, N.Y., 1959 March 10 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Nileson, Walter M.: TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Durham, N.C., 1959 June 2 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Riley, Lyman W.: TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Philadelphia, Pa., 1959 April 21 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Schorer, Mark (b. 1908): 2 TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Stanford, California, 1959 January 5, 1958 December 18 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Taylor, F. Jay: 2 TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Pineville, La., 1959 May 13, 20 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Volaik, J. Daivd: TLS to Charles A. Fenton, 1960 May 4 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Westlake, Neda M.: 3 TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; Philadelphia, Pa., 1959 March 31, April 28, May 8 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Widdemer, Margaret: TLS to Charles A. Fenton,; New York, N.Y., 1959 January 5 (Box 5, Folder 115)